A Guide to the Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart Papers 1791-1928
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart Papers 1791-1928
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
345
This collection consists of ca. 500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession number 345 was deposited in the Library in February 1939 by A. Stuart Robertson of Orange, Virginia. At his death in 1979, the papers were made a gift to the library on January 10, 1980, by Marvyn W. Robertson, his widow, and the follwing children or grandchildren of Margaret Briscoe Stuart Roberston: George M. Cochran, Margaret C. Hinch, Archibald H. Robertson, Alex F. Robertson, Jr., John S. Beard, and Alexander Robertson Beard.
Biographical/Historical Information
Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart, the son of Archibald and Eleanor Stuart, was born in Staunton, Virginia on April 2, 1807. He studied for one year at the College of William and Mary and then studied law and the University of Virginia, graduating in 1828. That same year he was admitted to practice law in Staunton, Virginia. He began his political career as a member of the Young Men's Convention held in support of Henry Clay at Washington in 1832. Afterwards, Stuart held a number of political offices, as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates in 1836, 1837, and 1838; a member of the U.S. House of Representatives from 1841 to 1843; a Presidential elector on the Clay ticket in 1844 and on the Taylor ticket in 1848; Secretary of the Interior under Millard Fillmore from September 12, 1850, to March 3, 1853; delegate in the National Convention of 1856; and as a member of the Virginia Convention in 1861.
Stuart opposed the secession of Virginia at the outbreak of the Civil War but remained loyal to Virginia and held various positions in the Confederate government. At the end of the Civil War, Stuart was one of the leaders of the first movement in the South to re-establish peaceful relations with the federal government, presiding at a mass meeting for that purpose at Stuanton, Virginia, on May 8, 1865. In the same year, Stuart was elected to Congress but was excluded by the "iron clad" oath. In December, 1868, Stuart began the "Committee of Nine," which, with the cooperation of President Grant, presuaded Congress to accept a compromise of "universal suffrage and universal amnesty." Virginia would accept Negro suffrage if the disfranchisement and test-oath clauses in the Underwood constitution were removed. Stuart also served as rector of the University of Virginia from 1876 to 1882 and 1884 to 1886, as a member of the Peabody educational fund, and as president of the Virginia Historical Society.
Scope and Content Information
This accession consists of ca. 500 items, 1791-1928, primarily pertaining to former Secretary of the Interior Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart (1807-1891) of Stuanton, Virginia. Correspondence, which comprises most of the collection, regards Staurt's education, law career, and political interests. Included are letters from Stuart to his parents while he was a student at the College of William and Mary and at the University of Virginia. The later correspondence concerns Millard Fillmore, Ulysses S. Grant, and James A. Garfield; Reconstruction in Virginia after the Civil War, including the debt funding controversy; the Whig and Know- Nothing (American) parties; Stuart's role in the fiscal bank vetoes of 1841; and the University of Virginia. Correspondents include Benjamin Johnson Barber, Judah Philip Benjamin, Thomas Hart Benton, Gerard Briscoe, Henry Clay, William Wilson Corcoran, Millard Fillmore, Thomas Walker Gilmer, Horace Greeley, Hugh Blair Grigsby, Rutherford B. Hayes, John H. Latane, Robert E. Lee, Leander J. McCormick, Hugh Holmes McGuire, John W. Mallet, John Barbee Minor, Rosewll Page, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Alexander River, Alexander F. Robertson, Wyndham Robertson, Conway Robinson, William Starke Rosencrans, Henry Rowe Schoolcraft, J.E.B. Stuart, THomas J. Stuart, John Tyler, Sr., William Henry Vanderbilt, and Robert C. Winthrop.
Arrangement
Items have been single-foldered for the most part (in some instances, one or more letters from the same person have been placed in the same folder) and are arranged chronologically. There is an alphabetical sliplist of all items in the collection.
Contents List
- Cornelius Baldwin to Mrs. Archibald (Betsy) Stuart 1791 Jul, ALS (Box 1)
- John Tyler to Archibald Stuart 1791 Nov 22, ALS (Box 1)
- Dr. Isaac Hall to Archibald Stuart 1792 Jul 10, ALS (Box 1)
- [Andrew] Lewis to Archibald Stuart 1793 Mar 13, ALS (Box 1)
- J. Pendleton to Archibald Stuart 1793 Aug 16, ALS (Box 1)
- Gerard Briscoe to Eleanor Stuart 1794 Aug 15, ALS (Box 1)
- John Allen to Archibald Stuart 1795 Sep 10, ALS (Box 1)
- John Allen to Archibald Stuart 1796 Now 30, ALS (Box 1)
- J[udith] Randolph to Mrs. Stewart (sic) 179[?], ANS (Box 1)
- Margaret Briscoe to Dr. Richard [Wates] 1802 Jul 26, 2 ADS (Box 1)
- Alexander Stuart and Alexander Hall 1809 Apr 28, ADS (Box 1)
- Agathe Alexander to Eleanor Stuart 1811 Aug 25, ALS (Box 1)
- Briscoe G. Baldwin to Eleanor Stuart 1814 Sep 15, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Stuart to Eleanor Stuart 1814 Sep 15, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Stuart to Eleanor Stuart 1814 Sep 19, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Stuart to Eleanor Stuart 1814 Sep 28, ALS (Box 1)
- William Black to Archibald Stuart 1814 Nov 4, ADS (Box 1)
- M. Love to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1815 Aug 7, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Archibald Staurt [1920-1825] Jan 31, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor Stuart [1820-1825] Now 19, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor Stuart 1823 Sep 9, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor Stuart 1825 Jan 30, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor Stuart 1825 Feb 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Mrs. Eleanor Stuart 1825 May 1, ALS (Box 1)
- Charles Lewis, Jr. to John Allen 1826 Jan 10, TD (Box 1)
- University of Virginia Absentee sheets of Alexander H. H. Stuart 1827-1828, 4 DS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's Permit to practice law in Virginia 1828 Aug 19, AMs (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's account of visit with Henry Clay in Kentucky 1839 Oct, ADS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's certificate of election to Congress 1841 May 3, AMs (Box 1)
- Thomas W[alker] Gilmer to Alexander H[ugh] H[olmes] Stuart 1841 Sep 24, enclosing ALS (copy), TWG to unknown constituent (Box 1)
- Thomas W[alker] Gilmer to Alexander H[ugh] H[olmes] Stuart 1841 Nov 15, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's appointment to House Foreign Affairs Committee 1842 Feb 14, DS (Box 1)
- George W. Jones to Henry Clay 1850 Nov 2, ALS (Box 1)
- Henry Clay to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1850 Nov 7 & 18, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to his mother [1850-1853] Feb 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Eleanor Stuart [1850-1853], LS (Box 1)
- John Baldwin to Millard Fillmore [1851] Jan 1, ALS (Box 1)
- Andrew Hunter to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1851 Jan 26, ALS (Box 1)
- Susan C. Armstrong to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1851 Aug 18, ALS (Box 1)
- John Minor Botts to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1851 Nov 30, ALS (Box 1)
- N. Quackenbush to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1851 Dec 31, ALS (Box 1)
- Joseph Glover Baldwin to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1852 Apr 16 & 1853 Apr 15, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Joseph G. Baldwin to John Baldwin 1852 Apr 27, ALS (Box 1)
- L.T. Waller to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1852 Jun 20, ALS (Box 1)
- Henry R. Schoolcraft to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1853 Feb 23, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Hart Benton to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1853 July 11, ALS (Box 1)
- A.C. Dickinson 1854 Jan 15, clipping (Box 1)
- Jeb Stuart to Alexander H. H. Stuart [1854] May 24, ALS (Box 1)
- Millard Fillmore to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1855 Jan 15, ALS (Box 1)
- Hugh Blair Grigsby to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1855 Sep 6, ALS (Box 1)
- A. Moseley to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 Apr 8, ALS (Box 1)
- Millard Fillmore to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 May 21, ALS (Box 1)
- S.G. Haven to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 Jun 29, ALS (Box 1)
- A. Stuart Brown to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 Jul 22, ALS (Box 1)
- Millard Fillmore to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 Aug 7, ALS (Box 1)
- Vespasian Ellis to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1856 Oct 10, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart- The Madison Letters[1856], Pamphlet (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to A.J. Crane, et. al. 1859 Mar 5, PMS (Box 1)
- James Lyons to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1859 Aug 6, ALS (Box 1)
- Elisha Whittlesey to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1859 Nov 14, ALS (Box 1)
- S.H. Parker to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1860 Mar 22, 2 AD (Box 1)
- Alexander Rives to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1860 Dec 5 & 1861 May 17, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's Speech to Va. Convention on Secession Ordinance [1861], Clipping (Box 1)
- Thomas Corwin to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1861 Jan 17, ALS (Box 1)
- J.E.B. Stuart to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1861 Dec 28, ALS (Box 1)
- Judah P. Benjamin to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1863 Mar 5, ALS (Box 1)
- J.E.B. Stuart to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1863 Dec 18, ALS (Box 1)
- John Brown Baldwin to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1864 Jan 21, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart To The Voters of the 6th Congressional District1865 Sep 14, PMs (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's appointment to commission on debt settlement with West Virginia 1866 Feb 28, AMsS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Horace Brady 1866 Dec 27, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart on Pacific Railroad 1866 Dec 28, Clipping (Box 1)
- William S. Rosencrans to Robert E. Lee 1868 Sep 6, 3 ALS (Box 1)
- John Echols to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1868 Sep 18, ALS (Box 1)
- Newspapers Clipping re Amnesty and Black Suffrage [1868], Clipping (Box 1)
- B. Johnson Barbour to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1869 Sep 10, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Millard Fillmore to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1869 Nov 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Robert Ridgeway to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1869 Feb 1 & 6, 2 LS (Box 1)
- Some Suggestions about the Public Debt by Alexander H. H. Stuart [1871-1880], AD (Box 1)
- Robert C. Winthrop to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1871 Feb 23 & 1873 Nov 13, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Conway Robinson to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1872 Jan 1, ALS (Box 1)
- John T. Stuart to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1842 Oct 20, ALS (Box 1)
- James P. Holcombe to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1873 Feb 6, ALS (Box 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1873 Nov 1, ALS (Box 1)
- A.D. Dickinson to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1873 Nov 20, ALS (Box 1)
- Hugh Blair Grigsby to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1873 Nov 24, ALS (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings 1873-1891, n.d. (Box 1)
- W.M. Ambler to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1874 [Jan] 24, ALS (Box 1)
- [Alexander H. H. Stuart] on Virginia's public debt 1875 Jun 8, Clipping (Box 1)
- James McDonald to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1875 Nov, DS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to [J. Marshall] Hanger 1875 Dec 7, Al (Box 1)
- James Lawson Kemper to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1876 Apr 10, DS (Box 1)
- Wm. Wilson Corcoran to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1876 Nov 8, ALS (Box 1)
- W.W. Henry to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1877 Jun 26, ALS (Box 1)
- Rutherford L. Hayes to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1879 16 May, ALS (Box 1)
- James D. Jomes to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1879 Jul 3, ALS (Box 1)
- Peabody Report on Education of Colored People 1880, PMs (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to William H. Vanderbilt 1881 Jul 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart to Leander J. McCormick 1881 Jul 4, ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's Tribute to Former President Garfield 1881 Sep 19 (Box 1)
- W.W. Corcoran to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1883 Dec 29, ALS (Box 1)
- Robert C. Winthrop to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1884 Nov 24- 1890 Jan 6, 7 ALS (Box 1)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart- List of Speeches.... [1885-1890], ALS (Box 1)
- Stauton Vindicator interview with Alexander H. H. Stuart 1886 Apr 16, TD (Box 1)
- Wyndham Robertson to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1886 Apr 26, ALS (Box 1)
- J.B. Beck to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1886 Jul 27, ALS (Box 1)
- John W. Noble to A.H. Fultz 1891 Feb 14, LS and D (Box 2)
- Board of Directors of Valley Mutual Libe Association of Va. on Alexander H. H. Stuart's death 1891 Feb 14, TMs (Box 2)
- Stauton Spectator re death of Alexander H. H. Stuart 1891 Feb 18, Clipping (Box 2)
- B.W. Lacy to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 20, ALS (Box 2)
- William J. Robertson to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 21, ALS (Box 2)
- L.L. Lewis to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 21, ALS (Box 2)
- [H.] C. Alexander to Mr. Alexander F. Robertson 1891 Feb 22, ALS (Box 2)
- John Echols to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 22, TLS (Box 2)
- Robert Stiles to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 23, ALS (Box 2)
- John B. Minor to Alexander H. H. Stuart 1891 Feb 23, ALS (Box 2)
- John W. Mallet to Thomas C. Elder 1891 Feb 25, ALS (Box 2)
- A.M. Randolph to Mrs McGuire 1891 Mar 17, ALS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson 1891, TD (Box 2)
- John H. Wadell- Biographical sketch of Alexander H. H. Stuart [1891], AD (Box 2)
- Alexander H. H. Stuart's sketch of Archibld Stuart [1891], PMs (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson [1891], AD (Box 2)
- Hugh Holmes McGuire to Alexander F. Robertson 1892 Nov 10, ALS (Box 2)
- Dr. Robertson-Biographical sketch of Alexander H. H. Stuart 1894, AMs (Box 2)
- Bartonm H. Wise to Alexander F. Robertson 189[7] Jan 5, ALS (Box 2)
- Barton H. Wise to Alexander 1897 Feb 1, ALS (Box 2)
- Barton H. Wise to Alexander 1897 Oct 25, ALS (Box 2)
- ....to "Dear Saunders" 18[?] Aug 26, AL (Box 2)
- Rosewell Page to Alexander F. Robertson 1925, TLS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson to F.B. Guest 1925 Jul 18, TLS (Box 2)
- Archibald Henderson to Ray B. Bradly, Sr. 1925 Dec 8, ALS (Box 2)
- Archibaled Henderson to Ray. B. Bradley, Sr. 1925 Dec 8, ALS (Box 2)
- E.L. Boyd to Alexander F. Robertson 1925 Dec 12, ALS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson- biography of Alexander H. H. Stuart [1925-1927], Clippins (Box 2)
- John H. Latane to Alexander F. Robertson 1926 Jan 4, ALS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson to John H. Latane 1926 Jan 4, TLS (Box 2)
- F.B.C. Bardlee to Alexander F. Robertson 1926 Jan 26, ALS (Box 2)
- Stuart Chevelier to Alexander F. Robertson 1926 Feb 6, TLS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson to Stuart Chevalier 1926 Feb 9, TLS (Box 2)
- Breckinridge Jones to Alexander F. Robertson 1926 Jun 7, TLS (Box 2)
- Alexander F. Robertson to Breckinridge Jones 1926 Jun 21, TLS (Box 2)
- E.G. Swem to Alexander F. Robertson 1926 Dec 28, 2 Pamphlets (Box 2)
- Alexander Bruce to Alexander F. Robertson 1927 May 19, ALS (Box 2)